<?xml version = '1.0' encoding = 'ISO-8859-1'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- $Id: cmdb.xml,v 1.5.2.1 2009-04-27 14:54:06 mh Exp $ --><chapter>
    <title>The CMDB - the central IT repository</title>
    <para>The configuration management database (CMDB) is not a database in the technical sense but a conceptual IT model, which is indispensable for efficient IT service management. All IT components and inventories are managed in the CMDB. Configuration management exceeds asset management, often incorrectly used as a synonym, as it does not only document assets from a financial point of view, but captures information regarding the relationship between components, specifications or their location. Thus IT support can quickly access information on the interdependence of IT services and the IT components (= configuration items = CIs) necessary for them.</para>
    <para>According to ITIL, a CMDB must feature the following functionalities:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
        <para>manual and, where applicable, automatic recording and modification of configuration items</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
        <para>description of the relationship and/or interdependence between CIs</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
        <para>change of CI attributes (e.g. serial numbers)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
        <para>location and user management for CIs</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
        <para>integration via the ITIL processes represented in the system</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>OTRS::ITSM meets all requirements stated above and offers numerous additional IT support functions in the CMDB.
</para>

    <sect1>
        <title>The OTRS::ITSM database model</title>
        <para>
            <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>database</screeninfo>
            <graphic fileref="screenshots/database.png" scale="50" srccredit="database" />
            </screenshot>
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
    <title>Services, at the core of everything</title>
    <para>Services such as &quot;standard IT workstation&quot;, &quot;e-mail&quot; or &quot;web access are IT products and should at all costs be compiled in a so called IT service catalog prior to the adoption of OTRS::ITSM. Such service catalogs are usually customer or company specific, can be structured hierarchically and should be formulated in a user friendly, i.e. easily understood, language, as they can be accessed by IT personnel (agents) and IT users (customers).
</para>
    <warning>
        <para>Service catalog design is a task which should not be underestimated. Our experience shows that it is highly recommendable to validate conceptual thoughts in a dry run first and transfer the service structures to OTRS::ITSM in a second step. It has proven of value to resort to external assistance, e.g. of ITIL practice experts. </para>
    </warning>
    <para>Example of (part of) a hierarchic IT service catalog specified in OTRS::ITSM as shown when a ticket is created </para>
    <para>
        <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>agent-phoneticket</screeninfo>
        <graphic fileref="screenshots/agent-phoneticket.png" scale="50" srccredit="agent-phoneticket - screenshot" />
        </screenshot>
    </para>
    <para>and in the administration area. </para>
    <para>
        <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>admin-service-managment-overview</screeninfo>
        <graphic fileref="screenshots/admin-service-managment-overview.png" scale="50" srccredit="admin-service-managment-overview - screenshot" />
        </screenshot>
    </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
    <title>Service levels and service level agreements</title>
    <para>Service levels and the respective agreements (service level agreements, SLAs) document quality pledges for IT services. SLAs are recorded and administered in the admin interface. </para>
    <para>
        <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>admin-sla-management-overview</screeninfo>
        <graphic fileref="screenshots/admin-sla-management-overview.png" scale="50" srccredit="admin-sla-management-overview - screenshot" />
        </screenshot>
    </para>
    <para>The following parameters can be recorded with every SLA: </para>
    <para>
        <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>admin-sla-management-edit</screeninfo>
        <graphic fileref="screenshots/admin-sla-management-edit.png" scale="50" srccredit="admin-sla-management-edit - screenshot" />
        </screenshot>
    </para>
    <para>OTRS::ITSM offers up to 99 different calendars by default to describe the various time zones for work or service times. The SLAs can be allocated to them (&quot;service level window&quot;). Various time spans can be entered (in minutes) which OTRS::ITSM uses to control notification and escalation:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
        <para>[ Response Time ]</para>
        <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>= reaction time with incidents</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>= start of service request procession (&quot;service request lead time&quot;)</para>
        </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>[ Update Time ]</para>
        <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>= notification time</para>
        </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>[ Solution Time ]</para>
        <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>= time elapsed until incidents are resolved (&quot;maximum time to repair&quot;, &quot;MTTR&quot;)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>= delivery time for service requests (&quot;delivery time&quot;)</para>
        </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>[ Min. Time Between Incidents ]</para>
        <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>= &quot;MTBI&quot;: minimal time between closure of the last incident ticket and recurrence of an incident for which the same SLA applies.</para>
        </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <warning>
        <para>If no values for the above-named times are entered in the SLAs, escalation is effected according to the time fields "response time", "update time" and "solution time" assigned to all queues!</para>
    </warning>
    <para>Important time values of OTRS::ITSM are based on the &quot;ITIL incident lifecycle&quot;:  </para>
    <para>
        <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>incident-lifecycle</screeninfo>
        <graphic fileref="screenshots/incident-lifecycle.png" scale="50" srccredit="incident-lifecycle - screenshot" />
        </screenshot>
    </para>
    <para>Source: OGC, ITIL Service Support Documentation</para>
    <para>The OTRS stats framework facilitates, among other things, the definition of the actual availability of a service from recorded incidents, which often serves as a performance figure in system-oriented SLAs. </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
    <title>Locations</title>
    <para>Locations can be structured hierarchically. All default location types are shown below. They can be adjusted to cater for individual needs:</para>
    <para>
        <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>admin-location-management</screeninfo>
        <graphic fileref="screenshots/admin-location-management.png" scale="50" srccredit="admin-location-management - screenshot" />
        </screenshot>
    </para>
    <para>Example of hierarchically structured locations:
    </para>
    <para>
        <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>admin-location-overview</screeninfo>
        <graphic fileref="screenshots/admin-location-overview.png" scale="50" srccredit="admin-location-overview - screenshot" />
        </screenshot>
    </para>
    </sect1>


    <sect1>
    <title>Configuration items</title>
    <para>Exemplary overview of recorded computer CIs (part) with current CI state:</para>
    <para>
        <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>agent-configuration-items</screeninfo>
        <graphic fileref="screenshots/agent-configuration-items.png" scale="50" srccredit="agent-configuration-items - screenshot" />
        </screenshot>
    </para>
    <para>Example of an individual CI view:</para>
    <para>
        <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>agent-configitem-management-link</screeninfo>
        <graphic fileref="screenshots/agent-configitem-management-link.png" scale="50" srccredit="agent-configitem-management-link - screenshot" />
        </screenshot>
    </para>
    <para>The graphic exemplarily shows the links between CIs. OTRS differentiates between bidirectional and nondirectional links. Whenever a CI is linked to another CMDB object, OTRS::ITSM automatically creates the respective reverse link.</para>
    <para>The OTRS::ITSM standard offers seven link types:</para>
    <para>
        <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>agent-configitem-management-link2</screeninfo>
        <graphic fileref="screenshots/agent-configitem-management-link2.png" scale="50" srccredit="agent-configitem-management-link2 - screenshot" />
        </screenshot>
    </para>
    <para>To link objects, the source object is chosen first, then the link type is defined and the target object chosen. The target object can be searched for using various criteria:
</para>
    <para>
        <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>agent-configitem-management-link3</screeninfo>
        <graphic fileref="screenshots/agent-configitem-management-link3.png" scale="50" srccredit="agent-configitem-management-link3- screenshot" />
        </screenshot>
    </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
    <title>Documents and knowledge database</title>
    <para>Using the FAQ system, which is an independent external module since OTRS 2.1, a knowledge database  can be designed and managed, e.g. for suggestions and/or procedures related to the resolution of known errors.</para>
    <para>Entries can be provided for internal use only, for all customers or the public. They can be created and sorted according to language or categories. The quality of FAQ articles can be evaluated by agents. The number of articles last created or last revised to be displayed can be configured without any limitations. All articles can be indexed for an efficient search. </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
    <title>Changes and amendments to the data model</title>
    <para>The data model can be adapted flexibly and can be extended with data types, attributes and even classes. Detailed information can be found in the section "The admin area of OTRS::ITSM" in this document or in "The admin area of OTRS" in the OTRS Admin Manual.
</para>
    <warning>
        <para>The design of a CMDB data model and the CIs to be managed within it is a task which should not be underestimated. Our experience shows that it is highly recommendable to validate conceptual thoughts in a dry run against the existing IT infrastructure first and change the OTRS::ITSM default data model and CI classes only afterwards. It has proven of value to resort to external assistance, e.g. of ITIL practice experts for CMDB design. </para>
    </warning>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
    <title>Ticket types and attributes</title>
    <para>With OTRS 2.2, native ticket types were introduced, which are used in OTRS::ITSM, too. In the ITIL sub-processes which can be structured in queues, tickets are classified on their ticket types. </para>
    <para>All ITIL processes to be implemented in later versions of OTRS::ITSM, e.g. change management, will be implemented in such a way. Ticket types such as RfC (&quot;Request for Change&quot;) could be created.
</para>
    <para>
        <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>admin-type-management</screeninfo>
        <graphic fileref="screenshots/admin-type-management.png" scale="50" srccredit="admin-type-management - screenshot" />
        </screenshot>
    </para>
    <warning>
        <para>In order to assure the consistency of the data managed in OTRS::ITSM, information created in the admin area of the system cannot be deleted as a general rule. If you want to deactivate such information, change the value in the respective listbox settings from "valid" to "invalid" or "invalid-temporarily". </para>
    </warning>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
