<?xml version='1.0' encoding='ISO-8859-1'?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- $Id: codesyntax.xml,v 1.10 2006-02-24 08:53:10 rk Exp $ -->

<chapter>
    <title>Coding Style Guide</title>
    <para>
        In order to preserve the consistent development of the OTRS project, we have set
        up a few guidelines regarding style.
    </para>
    <sect1 id="formatting">
        <title>Formatting</title>
        <para>
            TAB: We use 4 spaces. Examples for braces:
        </para>
        <programlisting format="linespecific">
if ($Condition) {
    Foo();
}
else {
    Bar();
}

while ($Condition == 1) {
    Foo();
}
        </programlisting>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="naming">
        <title>Naming</title>
        <para>
            Names and comments are written in English. Variables, Objects and Methods
            must be descriptive nouns or noun phrases with the first letter set upper case.
        </para>
        <programlisting format="linespecific">
e. g. @TicktIDs or $Output or BuildQueueView()
        </programlisting>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="source-code-header">
        <title>Source Code Header and Charset</title>
        <para>
            Attach the following header to each and every source file.
            Source files are saved in Charset ISO-8859-1.
        </para>
        <programlisting format="linespecific">
# --
# (file name) - a short description what it does.
# Copyright (C) (year) (name of author) (email of author)
# --
# $Id: codesyntax.xml,v 1.10 2006-02-24 08:53:10 rk Exp $
# --
# This software comes with ABSOLUTELY NO WARRANTY. For details, see
# the enclosed file COPYING for license information (GPL). If you
# did not receive this file, see http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl.txt.
# --
        </programlisting>
        <para>
            The following line is updated by the CVS:
        </para>
        <programlisting format="linespecific">
# $Id: codesyntax.xml,v 1.10 2006-02-24 08:53:10 rk Exp $
        </programlisting>

    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="version-comments">
        <title>Version Comments</title>
        <para>
            Some functions may not be available in the current framework version. Thus, sometimes
            settings have to be changed when a new module and framework version will be released.
            If you use version comments, you can search for information (e.g. using grep) on what must be changed when
            a new version is published. The keyword for version comments is 'FRAMEWORK'
            For perl use '#' and for xml use the xml comments.
        </para>
        <programlisting format="linespecific">
e.g. for perl-code
# FRAMEWORK-2.1: the function ID2UserName is first available in OTRS 2.1
        </programlisting>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
