<?xml version = '1.0' encoding = 'ISO-8859-1'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- $Id: commercial-services.xml,v 1.2 2008-08-14 17:06:36 ub Exp $ --><chapter>
    <title>Commercial services for OTRS::ITSM</title>
    <para>OTRS AG is manufacturer and source code owner of OTRS and all modules based upon it (e.g. OTRS::ITSM) and a professional service provider. Unlike those of proprietary software providers, OTRS AG's business model is not based on license fees: OTRS and OTRS::ITSM are available free of cost and we offer commercial services associated with the software applications instead. </para>
    <para>As your capable partner, we provide optimal support in all phases of your OTRS project design, realization and operation. We believe in deploying the most modern methods and our staff are highly skilled experts. This philosophy guarantees credit for powerful business applications and happy customers lauding our service quality (http://www.otrs.com/en/references/). </para>
    <sect1>
    <title>OTRS::ITSM consulting and implementation</title>
    <para>Are you planning to use OTRS::ITSM or have found out about OTRS::ITSM in a new product screening and want to assess the system's eligibility for your requirements. Or is your OTRS::ITSM evaluation completed and you want to make use of our consulting services to efficiently lead your project towards success.</para>
    <para>We offer extensive practical expertise in IT process consulting, software engineering, development, and ITIL compliant IT operations and support. Security and quality management for your project complement our service portfolio. You benefit from an extensive and quick knowledge transfer. </para>
    <para>Our services include:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
        <para>identification of your requirements and assistance with product evaluation</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>guidance on design and implementation of ITSM process and organizational structures</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para> ITIL assessments and support with ISO 20000 certification</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>ITIL trainings and coaching</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>ITIL implementation</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>compilation of IT service catalogs</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>CMDB design</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>installation &amp; configuration of OTRS::ITSM including integration with your existing system environment</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>review &amp; optimization of existing OTRS::ITSM installations</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>process and data migration from predecessor systems</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>release updates</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>specification of business and IT requirements and features, which exceed the given functional range of OTRS::ITSM </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>design and realization of project complimentary administrator and service agent trainings </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>advisory services regarding managed operations (ASP/SaaS) of OTRS::ITSM and application support</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
    <title>Software development</title>
    <para>One significant advantage of the open-source software OTRS::ITSM is its flexibility regarding potential extensions of the functional range. No "vendor lock-in", a typical risk of proprietary systems and protracted negotiations with the manufacturer about expanding the functional range or building interfaces apply with OTRS::ITSM. </para>
    <para>Experienced project managers and developers are at your disposal at any time to translate your requirements exceeding the functional range of OTRS::ITSM into business and IT specifications. We develop your features, program interfaces or upgrade existent functionalities according to your conception. </para>
    <para>Extensions, which are useful for other customers too, will be added to the standard in later releases. All parties involved benefit: OTRS::ITSM is even more powerful with the features "born" by you and other customers, and you save the cost of porting your features to new releases. </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
    <title>Application support</title>
    <para>The decision for an IT service management solution is an investment into the future which should not be underestimated, even if you opt for open-source software. A competent consulting partner is critical for the success of such an implementation project. Just as important, however, is a planned and successful porting of the solution to the life system and the lasting support of a reliable partner guaranteeing a faultless operating application service. </para>
    <para>We provide this continuous support and our service packages are tailored flexibly to meet your requirements. They offer differentiated response times for the various service level agreements with up to 24/7/365 support, 24/7/365 access to our support portal, and optional phone support. Please visit http://www.otrs.com/en/support/ for all details or contact our sales team at sales@otrs.com.</para>
    <para>You will only pay for the services you really need. Optional add-on packages, e.g. support via remote control or an extension of the application support services to other OTRS::ITSM instances can be booked if required.</para>
    <para>Our ITIL compliant operating Application Support Team is continually optimizing its processes and performance. Therefore, our service manager will contact you regularly to discuss your wishes and requirements regarding our services. The monthly service reporting in the service package of your choice serves as a base for these conversations.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
    <title>Managed application services (ASP/SaaS)</title>
    <para>You do not have to operate OTRS and/or OTRS::ITSM yourself. The products can be rented via the so called &quot;ASP&quot; (application service provisioning) resp. &quot;SaaS&quot; (software as a service) model from specialized companies.</para>
    <para>The customers (software users) are admitted internet access to exclusively rented OTRS systems and, where required, functional application support (see section above) at a fixed monthly price and can employ the application in their business to the contracted extent. No additional license fees apply as only open-source products are used.</para>
    <para>The application service provider operates IT infrastructure, systems and software ITIL compliantly and guarantees service quality according to the agreed service levels. The provider maintains the application system, (e.g. patches, backup, monitoring), and supports the customer with incidents and/or service requests such as consultation requests, software extensions or configuration requests. </para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
