<?xml version = '1.0' encoding = 'ISO-8859-1'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- $Id: incident-problem.xml,v 1.2 2008-08-14 17:06:36 ub Exp $ --><chapter>
    <title>Service desk, incident &amp; problem management</title>
    <para>The service desk (which, according to ITIL, is not a process but a function) is usually the ticket system's main field of application. All user messages and notifications from system monitoring and internal IT organization meet here. The ITIL service management process describes, closely interweaved with the service desk, which work steps, information, escalations and/or interfaces are relevant in connection with the processing of incidents or service requests. </para>
    <para>The incident and problem management processes within OTRS::ITSM are based on ITIL recommendations and ITIL terminology. At the same time, user comfort was a main consideration and terms known from OTRS have been retained as far as possible.</para>
    <para>
    <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>process-schema</screeninfo>
        <graphic fileref="screenshots/process-schema.png" scale="50" srccredit="process-schema - screenshot" />
    </screenshot>
    </para>
    <para>Source: ILX Group (www.ilxgroup.com)</para>
    <sect1>
    <title>Ticket generation, classification and prioritization</title>
    <para>At ticket generation in our case a phone ticket the following information can be registered additionally to the information implemented in OTRS:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
        <para>ticket type</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>relevant service</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>SLA</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>impact</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>priority</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Depending on the service selected, impact and priority are automatically submitted from the criticality impact priority matrix but can be overwritten. Requests can thus be prioritized higher or lower, which corresponds to  real day-to-day IT business requirements. </para>
    <para>Surely every IT service staff member knows a so called VIP customer who wants to be treated more equal than others and can be, this way. </para>
    <para>
        <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>agent-ticket-create</screeninfo>
        <graphic fileref="screenshots/agent-ticket-create.png" scale="50" srccredit="agent-ticket-create - screenshot" />
        </screenshot>
    </para>
    <para>By following the ticket content (zoom) link, detailed information about the ticket can be called up. All data relevant for IT support is consolidated in the right hand section:</para>
    <para>
        <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>agent-ticket-data-change</screeninfo>
        <graphic fileref="screenshots/agent-ticket-data-change.png" scale="50" srccredit="agent-ticket-data-change - screenshot" />
        </screenshot>
    </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
    <title>SLA relevant time information</title>
    <para>With the additional ITSM fields link, time information additional to the response, update and solution time provided in the SLA can be recorded and existing information can be changed:
</para>
    <para>
        <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>agent-ticket-additional-field</screeninfo>
        <graphic fileref="screenshots/agent-ticket-additional-field.png" scale="50" srccredit="agent-ticket-additional-field - screenshot" />
        </screenshot>
    </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
    <title>Allocate tickets (queues)</title>
    <para>The OTRS::ITSM queues can be adapted flexibly to your organizational structures. They can follow the vertical scheme of service desk, first, second and third level support often used in IT service support or be configured in a process oriented manner based on the ticket life cycle of generation, processing, closure and post-processing. </para>
    <para>Contrary to OTRS versions prior to version 2.2, ticket escalation in OTRS::ITSM is based first of all on the response, update and recovery times provided in the SLA.
If no values are provided in the SLA, escalation is effected based on the queues and time information stored in them.  </para>
    <para>Tickets can be moved by choosing a new queue in the bottom right corner of the ticket view.</para>
    <para>
        <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>agent-ticket-queue</screeninfo>
        <graphic fileref="screenshots/agent-ticket-queue.png" scale="50" srccredit="agent-ticket-queue - screenshot" />
        </screenshot>
    </para>
    <warning>
        <para>The design of a queue structure is a task which should not be underestimated. Our experience shows that it is highly recommendable to validate conceptual thoughts in a dry run against the existing IT infrastructure before configuring OTRS::ITSM. It has proven of value to resort to external assistance, e.g. of OTRS or ITIL practice experts for the queue design.
</para>
    </warning>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
    <title>Change ticket data</title>
    <para>All changes to the ticket can be effected just as in OTRS using the links below the navigation bar. </para>
    <para>
        <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>agent-ticket-data-change</screeninfo>
        <graphic fileref="screenshots/agent-ticket-data-change.png" scale="50" srccredit="agent-ticket-data-change - screenshot" />
        </screenshot>
    </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
    <title>Approvals and decisions</title>
    <para>In many cases, especially with service requests, decisions have to be taken before requests can be implemented. Depending on the competence framework, decisions are either taken directly by the service staff (standard changes) or the approval of a supervising manager must be obtained first. This is primarily the case with permission changes (a user wants to access a restricted file system directory) or cost generating requests (new laptop).</para>
    <para>In OTRS::ITSM approvals and refusals are shown via the decision link and are permanently saved with the ticket:</para>
    <para>
        <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>agent-ticket-decision</screeninfo>
        <graphic fileref="screenshots/agent-ticket-decision.png" scale="50" srccredit="agent-ticket-decision - screenshot" />
        </screenshot>
    </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
    <title>Generation of problem tickets from incidents</title>
    <para>To generate a problem ticket from one or more incidents, generate a new ticket and link it with the relevant incident tickets. This way, the underlying incidents can be processed individually, can be closed with a workaround if necessary and later be substituted with a permanent solution.</para>
    <para>A merging of incident and problem tickets obscures the reporting and complicates controlling and the continuous improvement of the IT services.
</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
    <title>Ticket closure</title>
    <para>Unlike the OTRS standard, OTRS::ITSM facilitates ITIL compliant ticket closure with a workaround.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
    <title>Processing of service requests</title>
    <para>Service requests are incidents, too and are processed equally. They are distinguishable from disruptions because of the ticket type Incident::Service Request.</para>
    <para>Another difference, the SLA relevant times, is explained in greater detail in the service levels and service level agreements section.</para>
    <para>
        <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>agent-service-request</screeninfo>
        <graphic fileref="screenshots/agent-service-request.png" scale="50" srccredit="agent-service-request - screenshot" />
        </screenshot>
    </para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
