<?xml version = '1.0' encoding = 'ISO-8859-1'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- $Id: installation.xml,v 1.8 2008-08-21 09:47:23 ub Exp $ --><chapter>
    <title>Installing OTRS::ITSM</title>
    <para>OTRS framework 2.3 must be installed prior to the installation of OTRS::ITSM. All necessary information, options and installation procedures are depicted in the OTRS Admin Manual.
</para>
    <warning>
    <para>Installation of the OTRS::ITSM packages requires empty free-text fields 13-16 and free-time fields 3-6 in the complete system! </para>
    </warning>

    <sect1>

        <title>Installation</title>

        <para>As soon as OTRS 2.3 or later is ready, sign on as administrator. Using the package manager in the admin area or via ftp://ftp.otrs.org/pub/otrs/itsm/packages12/ and install the ITSM packages in the following order: </para>
        <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>GeneralCatalog</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>ITSMCore</para>
        </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>If you have internet access from OTRS, use the online repository [--OTRS::ITSM 1.2 Master--] to install the packages below. Otherwise download the packages and use the package manager to install the packages:</para>

        <itemizedlist>

            <listitem>
                <para>ITSMIncidentProblemManagement</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>ITSMConfigurationManagement</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>ITSMServiceLevelManagement</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>ImportExport</para>
            </listitem>

        </itemizedlist>

        <para>You can find further information about the installation process here: http://ftp.otrs.org/pub/otrs/itsm/INSTALL-1.2.ITSM</para>
        <para>
        <screenshot>
            <screeninfo>index.pl - Admin Paket Manager</screeninfo>
            <graphic fileref="screenshots/admin-packagemanager.png" scale="50" srccredit="Admin Paket Manager - screenshot" />
        </screenshot>
        </para>

    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Upgrade</title>

        <para>
            If an older version than OTRS::ITSM 1.1 is installed, update the system to the latest version 1.1 first.
        </para>
        <para>
            If OTRS::ITSM 1.1 is installed already, update your OTRS 2.2 framework to version 2.3 BEFORE you
            update OTRS:ITSM. To do so, download the latest OTRS 2.3 framework and follow the instructions in the file UPGRADING.
            After that, log in to your system and use the package manager to install
            the package ITSMUpgradeTo12. You can download it manually or use the
            online repository. Ignore all error messages about not correctly installed
            old ITSM packages. This package will install all needed packages to update your system to an
            OTRS::ITSM 1.2 version, and it will migrate all your data.
        </para>

        <para>
            Note: The upgrade can take several minutes! Please do not stop the upgrade process once it is running!
        </para>

        <para>
            To upgrade an already installed OTRS::ITSM 1.2, use the package manager in the admin area.
            If you have internet access from OTRS, use the online repository [--OTRS::ITSM 1.2 Master--]
            to install newer packages. An 'upgrade' link next to the package name indicates if a newer package
            is available.
         </para>
         <para>
            Otherwise download the packages and use the package manager to install the packages.
            Do not uninstall your current packages, or your data will get lost!
        </para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
