<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- $Id: loader.xml,v 1.2 2010-09-15 07:28:22 mg Exp $ -->

<section id="loader">
    <title>The CSS and JavaScript "Loader"</title>
    <para>
        Starting with OTRS 3.0, the CSS and JavaScript code in OTRS grew
        to a large amount. To be able to satisfy both development concerns
        (good maintainability by a large number of separate files) and
        performance issues (making few HTTP requests and serving minified
        content without unneccessary whitespace and documentation)
        hat to be addressed. To achieve these goals, the Loader was invented.
    </para>

    <section>
        <title>How it works</title>
        <para>
            To put it simple, the Loader
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        determines for each request
                        precisely which CSS and JavaScript files are needed at the client
                        side by the current application module
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        collects all the relevant data
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        minifies the data, removing unneccessary whitespace and documentation
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        serves it to the client in only a few HTTP reqests instead of many
                        individual ones, allowing the client to cache these snippets in the browser cache
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        perform these tasks in a highly performing way, utilizing the caching
                        mechanisms of OTRS.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>
            Of course, there is a little bit more detailed involved, but this should suffice
            as a first overview.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Basic Operation</title>
        <para>
            With the configuration settings <literal>Loader::Enabled::CSS</literal>
            and <literal>Loader::Enabled::JavaScript</literal>, the loader can be turned
            on and off for JavaScript and CSS, respectively (it is on by default).
        </para>
        <warning>
            <para>
                Because of rendering problems in Internet Explorer, the Loader cannot be turned
                off for CSS files for this client browser (config setting will be overridden).
                Up to version 8, Internet Explorer cannot handle more than 32 CSS files on a page.
            </para>
        </warning>
        <para>
            To learn about how the Loader works, please turn it off in your OTRS installation
            with the aforementioned configuration settings. Now look at the source code of
            the application module that you are currently using in this OTRS system (after a
            reload, of course). You will see that there are many CSS files loaded in the
            <literal>&lt;head&gt;</literal> section of the page, and many JavaScript files
            at the bottom of the page, just before the closing <literal>&lt;/body&gt;</literal>
            element.
        </para>
        <para>
            Having the content like this in many individual files with a readable formatting
            makes the development much easier, and even possible at all. However, this has the
            disadvantage of a large number of HTTP requests (network latency has a big effect)
            and unneccessary content (whitespace and documentation) which needs to be transferred
            to the client.
        </para>
        <para>
            The Loader solves this problem by performing the steps outlined in the short description
            above. Please turn on the Loader again and reload your page now. Now you can see that there are only
            very few CSS and JavaScript tags in the HTML code, like this:

            <programlisting><![CDATA[
<!--CommonJS-->
<script type="text/javascript" src="/otrs30-dev-web/js/js-cache/CommonJS_d16010491cbd4faaaeb740136a8ecbfd.js"></script>
<!--/CommonJS-->

<!--ModuleJS-->
<script type="text/javascript" src="/otrs30-dev-web/js/js-cache/ModuleJS_b54ba9c085577ac48745f6849978907c.js"></script>
<!--/ModuleJS-->
            ]]></programlisting>

            What just happened? During the original request generating the HTML code for this page,
            the Loader generated these two files (or took them from the cache) and put the
            shown <literal>&lt;script&gt;</literal> tags on the page which link to these files,
            instead of linking to all relevant JavaScript files separately (as you saw it without
            the loader being active).
        </para>
        <para>
            The CSS section looks a little more complicated:

            <programlisting><![CDATA[
<!--CommonCSS-->
    <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="/otrs30-dev-web/skins/Agent/default/css-cache/CommonCSS_00753c78c9be7a634c70e914486bfbad.css" />
<!--/CommonCSS-->

<!--CommonCSS_IE7-->
<!--[if IE 7]>
    <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="/otrs30-dev-web/skins/Agent/default/css-cache/CommonCSS_IE7_59394a0516ce2e7359c255a06835d31f.css" />
    <![endif]-->
<!--/CommonCSS_IE7-->

<!--CommonCSS_IE8-->
<!--[if IE 8]>
    <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="/otrs30-dev-web/skins/Agent/default/css-cache/CommonCSS_IE8_ff58bd010ef0169703062b6001b13ca9.css" />
    <![endif]-->
<!--/CommonCSS_IE8-->
            ]]></programlisting>

            The reason is that Internet Explorer 7 and 8 need special treatment because
            of their lacking support of web standard technologies. So we have some normal CSS,
            and some that is inside of so-called "conditional comments" which cause it to be loaded
            <emphasis>only</emphasis> by Internet Explorer 7/8. All other browsers will ignore it.
        </para>
        <para>
            Now we have outlined how the loader works. Let's look at how you can utilize that in
            your own OTRS extensions by adding configuration data to the loader, telling it to
            load additional or alternative CSS or JavaScript content.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id="loader-javascript">
        <title>Configuring the Loader: JavaScript</title>
        <para>
            To be able to operate correctly, the Loader needs to know which content it has to
            load for a particular OTRS application module. First, it will look for JavaScript
            files which <emphasis>always</emphasis> have to be loaded, and then it looks for
            special files which are only relevant for the current application module.
        </para>
        <section id="loader-common-javascript">
            <title>Common JavaScript</title>
            <para>
                The list of JavaScript files to be loaded is configured in the configuration settings
                <literal>Loader::Agent::CommonJS</literal> (for the agent interface) and
                <literal>Loader::Customer::CommonJS</literal> (for the customer interface).
            </para>
            <para>
                These settings are designed as hashes, so that OTRS extensions can add their own
                hash keys for additional content to be loaded. Let's look at an example:

                <programlisting><![CDATA[
<ConfigItem Name="Loader::Agent::CommonJS###000-Framework" Required="1" Valid="1">
    <Description Translatable="1">List of JS files to always be loaded for the agent interface.</Description>
    <Group>Framework</Group>
    <SubGroup>Core::Web</SubGroup>
    <Setting>
        <Array>
            <Item>thirdparty/json/json2.js</Item>
            <Item>thirdparty/jquery-1.4.2/jquery.js</Item>

            ...

            <Item>Core.App.js</Item>
            <Item>Core.Agent.js</Item>
            <Item>Core.Agent.Search.js</Item>
        </Array>
    </Setting>
</ConfigItem>
                ]]></programlisting>

                This is the list of JavaScript files which always need to be loaded
                for the agent interface of OTRS.
            </para>
            <para>
                To add new content which is supposed to be loaded always in the agent interface,
                just add an XML configuration file with another hash entry:

                <programlisting><![CDATA[
<ConfigItem Name="Loader::Agent::CommonJS###100-CustomPackage" Required="0" Valid="1">
    <Description Translatable="1">List of JS files to always be loaded for the agent interface for package "CustomPackage".</Description>
    <Group>Framework</Group>
    <SubGroup>Core::Web</SubGroup>
    <Setting>
        <Array>
            <Item>CustomPackage.App.js</Item>
        </Array>
    </Setting>
</ConfigItem>
                ]]></programlisting>

                Simple, isn't it?
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="loader-module-javascript">
            <title>Module-Specific JavaScript</title>
            <para>
                Not all JavaScript is usable for all application modules of OTRS.
                Therefore it is possible to specify module-specific JavaScript files.
                Whenever a certain module is used (such as <literal>AgentDashboard</literal>),
                the module-specific JavaScript for this module will also be loaded.
                The configuration is done in the frontend module registration in the
                XML configurations.
                Again, an example:

                <programlisting><![CDATA[
<ConfigItem Name="Frontend::Module###AgentDashboard" Required="0" Valid="1">
    <Description Translatable="1">Frontend module registration for the agent interface.</Description>
    <Group>Framework</Group>
    <SubGroup>Frontend::Agent::ModuleRegistration</SubGroup>
    <Setting>
        <FrontendModuleReg>
            <Description>Agent Dashboard</Description>
            <Title></Title>
            <NavBarName>Dashboard</NavBarName>
            <NavBar>
                <Description Translatable="1"></Description>
                <Name Translatable="1">Dashboard</Name>
                <Link>Action=AgentDashboard</Link>
                <NavBar>Dashboard</NavBar>
                <Type>Menu</Type>
                <Description Translatable="1"></Description>
                <Block>ItemArea</Block>
                <AccessKey>d</AccessKey>
                <Prio>50</Prio>
            </NavBar>
            <Loader>
                <JavaScript>thirdparty/flot/excanvas.js</JavaScript>
                <JavaScript>thirdparty/flot/jquery.flot.js</JavaScript>
                <JavaScript>Core.UI.Chart.js</JavaScript>
                <JavaScript>Core.UI.DnD.js</JavaScript>
                <JavaScript>Core.Agent.Dashboard.js</JavaScript>
            </Loader>
        </FrontendModuleReg>
    </Setting>
</ConfigItem>
                ]]></programlisting>

                It is possible to put a <literal>&lt;Loader&gt;</literal> tag
                in the frontend module registrations which may contain
                <literal>&lt;JavaScript&gt;</literal> tags, one for each file
                that is supposed to be loaded for this application module.
            </para>
            <para>
                Now you have all information you need to configure the way the Loader
                handles JavaScript code.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Configuring the Loader: CSS</title>
        <para>
            The loader handles CSS files very similar to JavaScript files, as described
            in the previous <link linkend="loader-javascript">section</link>, and extending
            the settings works in the same way too.
        </para>

        <section>
            <title>Common CSS</title>
            <para>
                The way common CSS is handled is very similar to the way
                <link linkend="loader-common-javascript">common JavaScript</link>
                is loaded. Here, the configuration settings are called
                <literal>Loader::Agent::CommonCSS</literal> and
                <literal>Loader::Customer::CommonCSS</literal>, respectively.
            </para>
            <para>
                However, as we already noted above, Internet Explorer 7 and 8
                (and for the customer interface also 6) need special treatment.
                That's why there are special configuration settings for them, to
                specify common CSS which should only be loaded in these browsers.
                The respective settings are
                <literal>Loader::Agent::CommonCSS::IE7</literal>,
                <literal>Loader::Agent::CommonCSS::IE8</literal>,
                <literal>Loader::Customer::CommonCSS::IE6</literal>,
                <literal>Loader::Customer::CommonCSS::IE7</literal> and
                <literal>Loader::Customer::CommonCSS::IE8</literal>.
            </para>
            <para>
                An example:

                <programlisting><![CDATA[
<ConfigItem Name="Loader::Agent::CommonCSS::IE8###000-Framework" Required="1" Valid="1">
    <Description Translatable="1">List of IE8-specific CSS files to always be loaded for the agent interface.</Description>
    <Group>Framework</Group>
    <SubGroup>Core::Web</SubGroup>
    <Setting>
        <Array>
            <Item>Core.OverviewSmall.IE8.css</Item>
        </Array>
    </Setting>
</ConfigItem>
                ]]></programlisting>

                This is the list of common CSS files for the agent interface which
                should only be loaded in Internet Explorer 8.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Module-Specific CSS</title>
            <para>
                Module-specific CSS is handled very similar to the way
                <link linkend="loader-module-javascript">module-specific JavaScript</link>
                is handled. It is also configured in the frontend module registrations. Example:

                <programlisting><![CDATA[
<ConfigItem Name="Frontend::Module###Admin" Required="0" Valid="1">
    <Description Translatable="1">Frontend module registration for the agent interface.</Description>
    <Group>Framework</Group>
    <SubGroup>Frontend::Admin::ModuleRegistration</SubGroup>
    <Setting>
        <FrontendModuleReg>
            <Group>admin</Group>
            <Description>Admin-Area</Description>
            <Title></Title>
            <NavBarName>Admin</NavBarName>
            <NavBar>
                <Type>Menu</Type>
                <Description Translatable="1"></Description>
                <Block>ItemArea</Block>
                <Name Translatable="1">Admin</Name>
                <Link>Action=Admin</Link>
                <NavBar>Admin</NavBar>
                <AccessKey>a</AccessKey>
                <Prio>10000</Prio>
            </NavBar>
            <NavBarModule>
                <Module>Kernel::Output::HTML::NavBarModuleAdmin</Module>
            </NavBarModule>
            <Loader>
                <CSS>Core.Agent.Admin.css</CSS>
                <CSS_IE7>Core.Agent.AdminIE7.css</CSS_IE7>
                <JavaScript>Core.Agent.Admin.SysConfig.js</JavaScript>
            </Loader>
        </FrontendModuleReg>
    </Setting>
</ConfigItem>
                ]]></programlisting>

                Here we have a module (the admin overview page of the agent interface)
                which has special JavaScript, normal CSS
                (tagname <literal>&lt;CSS&gt;</literal>) and special CSS for
                Internet Explorer 7 (tagname <literal>&lt;CSS_IE7&gt;</literal>).
                All of these need to be loaded in addition to the common JavaScript
                and CSS defined for the agent interface.
            </para>
            <para>
                It is also possible to specify module-specific CSS for Internet Explorer 8
                (tagname <literal>&lt;CSS_IE8&gt;</literal>) and, in the case of the customer interface,
                for Internet Explorer 6 (tagname <literal>&lt;CSS_IE6&gt;</literal>).
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
</section>
