<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

<section id="accessibility">
    <title>Accessibility Guide</title>

    <para>
        This document is supposed to explain basics about accessibility issues and
        give guidelines for contributions to OTRS.
    </para>

    <section>
        <title> Accessibility Basics</title>

        <section>
            <title>
                What is Accessibility?
            </title>
            <para>
                Accessibility is a general term used to describe the degree to which a product, device, service, or
                environment is accessible by as many people as possible.
                Accessibility can be viewed as the "ability to access" and possible benefit of some
                system or entity. Accessibility is often used to focus on people with disabilities
                and their right of access to entities, often through use of assistive technology.
            </para>
            <para>
        In the context of web development, accessibility has a focus on enabling people with impariments
        full access to web interfaces. For example, this group of people can include partially visually
        impaired or completely blind people. While the former can still partially use the GUI, the latter
        have to completely rely on assistive technologies such as software which reads the screen to them (screen readers).
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>
                Why is it important for OTRS?
            </title>
            <para>
                To enable impaired users access to OTRS systems is a valid goal in itself. It shows respect.
            </para>
            <para>
                Furthermore, fulfilling accessibility standards is becoming increasingly important in the public sector
                (government institutions) and large companies, which both belong to the target markets of OTRS.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>
                How can I successfully work on accessibility issues even if I am not disabled?
            </title>
            <para>
                This is very simple. Pretend to be blind.
            </para>
            <para>
                Don't
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            use the Mouse and
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            look at the screen.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <para>
                Then try to use OTRS with the help of a screen reader and your keyboard only.
                This should give you an idea of how it will feel for a blind person.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
        <title>
            Ok, but I don't have a screen reader!
        </title>
        <para>
            While commercial screen readers such as JAWS (perhaps the best known one) can be extremely expensive,
            there are OpenSource screen readers which you can install and use:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <ulink url="http://www.nvda-project.org/">NVDA</ulink>, a screen reader for Windows.
                        (Use the 2010.beta1 or any later version as
                        this has better support for the web accessibility standards).
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <ulink url="http://live.gnome.org/Orca">ORCA</ulink>, a screen reader for Gnome/Linux.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>
            Now you don't have an excuse any more. ;)
        </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title> Accessibility Standards</title>
        <para>
            This section is included for reference only, you do not have to study the standards
            themselves to be able to work on accessibility issues in OTRS.
            We'll try to extract the relevant guidelines in this document.
        </para>

        <section>
            <title>Web Content Accessibility Guidelines (WCAG)</title>

            <para>
                This W3C standard gives general guidelines for how to create accessible web pages.

                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <ulink url="http://www.w3.org/TR/WCAG20/">WCAG 2.0</ulink>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <ulink url="http://www.w3.org/WAI/WCAG20/quickref/">How to Meet WCAG 2.0</ulink>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <ulink url="http://www.w3.org/TR/UNDERSTANDING-WCAG20/">Understanding WCAG 2.0</ulink>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <para>
                WCAG has different levels of accessibility support.
                We currently plan to support level A, as AA and AAA
                deal with matters that seem not relevant for OTRS.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title> Accessible Rich Internet Applications (WAI-ARIA) 1.0</title>
            <para>
                This standard (ist is still in draft status, in fact) deals
                with the special issues arising from the shift away from static
                content to dynamic web applications. It deals with questions like
                how a user can be notified of changes in the user interface
                resulting from AJAX requests, for example.

                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <ulink url="http://www.w3.org/TR/wai-aria/">WAI-ARIA 1.0</ulink>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title> Implementation guidelines</title>

        <section><title>Provide alternatives for non-text content</title>
            <para>
                Goal: <emphasis>All non-text content that is presented to the user has a
                text alternative that serves the equivalent purpose</emphasis> (WCAG 1.1.1)

            </para>
            <para>
                It is very important to understand that screen readers can only
                present textual information and available metadata to the user.
                To give you an example, whenever a screen reader sees
                <literal>&lt;a href="#" class="CloseLink"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</literal>,
                it can only read "link" to the user, but not the purpose of this link.
                With a slight improvement, it would be accessible:
                <literal>&lt;a href="#" class="CloseLink" title="Close this widget"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</literal>.
                In this case the user would hear "link close this widget", voila!
            </para>
            <para>
                It is important to always formulate the text in a most "speaking" way.
                Just imagine it is the only information that you have. Will it help you?
                Can you understand its purpose just by hearing it?
            </para>
            <para>
                Please follow these rules when working on OTRS:

                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <emphasis>Rul:</emphasis>: Wherever possible, use speaking texts and formulate in real,
                            understandable and precise sentences. "Close this widget" is much better than
                            "Close", because the latter is redundant.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <emphasis>Rule</emphasis>: Links always must have either text content that is
                            spoken by the screen reader (<literal>&lt;a href="#" &gt;Delete this entry&lt;/a&gt;</literal>),
                            or a title attribute (<literal>&lt;a href="#" title="Close this widget"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</literal>).
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <emphasis>Rule</emphasis>: Images must always have an alternative text
                            that can be read to the user (<literal>&lt;img src="house.png" alt="Image of a house" /&gt;</literal>).
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>

            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Make navigation easy</title>

            <para>
                Goal: <emphasis>allow the user to easily navigate the current page and the entire application.</emphasis>
            </para>
            <para>
                The <literal>title</literal> tag is the first thing a user hears from the screen reader when opening a web page.
                For OTRS, there is also always just one <literal>h1</literal> element on the page, indicating the current page
                (it contains part of the information from <literal>title</literal>).
                This navigational information helps the user to understand where they are, and what the purpose of the current page is.
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Rule</emphasis>: Always give a precise title to the page that allows the user to understand where they currently are.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>
                Screen readers can use the built-in document structure of HTML
                (headings <literal>h1</literal> to <literal>h6</literal>) to determine the
                structure of a document and to allow the user to jump around from section to section.
                However, this is not enough to reflect the structure of a dynamic web application.
                That's why ARIA defines several "landmark" roles that can be given to elements to
                indicate their navigational significance.
                To keep the validity of the HTML documents, the role attributes (ARIA landmark roles)
                are not inserted into the source code directly, but instead by classes which will
                later be used by the JavaScript functions in OTRS.UI.Accessibility to set the
                corresponding role attributes on the node.
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Rule</emphasis>: Use WAI ARIA Landmark Roles to structure the content for screenreaders
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Banner: <literal>&lt;div class="ARIARoleBanner"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</literal>
                                    will become <literal>&lt;div class="ARIARoleBanner" role="banner"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</literal>
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Navigation: <literal>&lt;div class="ARIARoleNavigation"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</literal>
                                    will become <literal>&lt;div class="AriaRoleNavigation" role="navigation"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</literal>
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Search function: <literal>&lt;div class="ARIARoleSearch"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</literal>
                                    will become <literal>&lt;div class="ARIARoleSearch" role="search"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</literal>
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Main application area: <literal>&lt;div class="ARIARoleMain"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</literal>
                                    will become <literal>&lt;div class="ARIARoleMain" role="main"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</literal>
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    Footer: <literal>&lt;div class="ARIARoleContentinfo"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</literal>
                                    will become <literal>&lt;div class="ARIARoleContentinfo" role="contentinfo"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</literal>
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>
                For navigation inside of <literal>&lt;form&lt;</literal> elements,
                it is neccessary for the impaired user to know what each input
                elements purpose is. This can be achieved by using standard HTML
                <literal>&lt;label&gt;</literal> elements which create a link
                between the label and the form element.
                When an input element gets focus, the screen reader will
                usually read the connected label, so that the agent can hear its exact purpose.
                An additional benefit for seeing users is that they can click on the label,
                and the input element will get focus (escpecially helpful for checkboxes, for example).
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Rule</emphasis>: Provide <literal>&lt;label&gt;</literal>
                        elements for *all* form element (input, select, textarea) fields.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: <literal>&lt;label for="date"&gt;Date:&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type="text" name="date" id="date"/&gt;</literal>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Make interaction possible</title>
            <para>
                Goal: <emphasis>Allow the user to perform all interactions just by using the keyboard.</emphasis>
            </para>
            <para>
                While it is technically possible to create interactions with JavaScript on
                arbitrary HTML elements, this must be limited to elements that a user can
                interact with by using the keyboard.
                Specifically, they need to be able to give focus to the element and to interact with it.
                For example, a push button to toggle a widget should not be realized by using a
                <literal>span</literal> element with an attached JavaScript <literal>onclick</literal>
                event listener, but it should be (or contain) an <literal>a</literal> tag to make it
                clear to the screen reader that this element can cause interaction.
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Rule</emphasis>: For interactions, always use elements that can receive focus,
                        such as <literal>a</literal>, <literal>input</literal>, <literal>select</literal> and <literal>button</literal>.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Rule</emphasis>: Make sure that the user can always identify the nature
                        of the interaction (see rules about non-textual content and labelling of form elements).
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>
                Goal: <emphasis>Make dynamic changes known to the user.</emphasis>
            </para>
            <para>
                A special area of accessibility problems are dynamic changes in the user interface,
                either by JavaScript or also by AJAX calls.
                The screen reader will not tell the user about changes without special precautions.
                This is a difficult topic and cannot yet be completely explained here.
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Rule</emphasis>: Always use the validation framework <literal>OTRS.Validate</literal> for form validation.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        This will make sure that the error tooltips are being read by the screen reader.
                        That way the blind agent a) knows the item which has an error and b) get a text describing the error.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Rule</emphasis>: Use the function <literal>OTRS.UI.Accessibility.AudibleAlert()</literal>
                        to notify the user about other important UI changes.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Rule</emphasis>: Use the <literal>OTRS.UI.Dialog</literal> framework
                        to create modal dialogs. These are already optimized for accessibility.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>General screen reader optimizations</title>
            <para>
                Goal: <emphasis>Help screen readers with their work.</emphasis>
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Rule</emphasis>: Each page must identify its own main language
                        so that the screenreader can choose the right speech synthesis engine.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example: <literal>&lt;html lang="fr"&gt;...&lt;/html&gt;</literal>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
    </section>

</section>
