<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- $Id: translate-docs.xml,v 1.2 2010-12-21 15:58:09 mg Exp $ -->

<section id="translating-docs">
    <title>Translating the Documentation</title>

    <para>
        The OTRS admin manual can be translated. The workflow is like this:
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The original documentation is written in English, in docbook XML format.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The tool <ulink url="http://po4a.alioth.debian.org/">po4a</ulink>
                    extracts gettext translation files from that (.po). These files can be
                    edited with existing helpful tools like <ulink url="http://www.poedit.net/">Poedit</ulink>.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    These files can be translated and will be updated on changes in the
                    English source files without loosing existing translations.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    From the translation files, translated docbook XML filed can be generated
                    for the different languages (again with po4a).
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        This process has the benefit of keeping track of updates in the original source files.
        Only additions and updates have to be retranslated.
    </para>

    <para>
        The git repository for the admin documentation can be found
        <ulink url="https://github.com/OTRS/doc-admin">on github</ulink>.
        Inside of this repository, there is the
        <ulink url="https://github.com/OTRS/doc-admin/tree/master/i18n">directory with the translation files</ulink>.
    </para>

    <para>
        To start a new translation, download the translation template file
        <ulink url="https://github.com/OTRS/doc-admin/blob/master/i18n/doc-admin.pot">doc-admin.pot</ulink>
        from git, save it and rename the file to <literal>doc-admin.$Lanugage.po</literal>
        (e. g. <literal>doc-admin.de.po</literal> for German).
    </para>
    <para>
        To improve an existing translation, you can download the <literal>doc-admin.$Lanugage.po</literal> file
        for this lanugage and work on this. If there are questions on how the translation should be made, you can use
        <literal>doc-admin.de.po</literal> as a reference.
    </para>
    <para>
        It is important that the structure of the generated XML stays intact.
        So if the original string is "Edit &lt;filename&gt;Kernel/Config.pm&lt;/filename&gt;",
        then the German translation has to be "&lt;filename&gt;Kernel/Config.pm&lt;/filename&gt; bearbeiten",
        keeping the the XML tags. Scripts and examples usually do not have to be translated (so you can just copy
        the source text to the translation text field in this case).
    </para>
    <para>
        To coordinate translation efforts and to send in your translated .po files, please use the
        <ulink url="http://lists.otrs.org/cgi-bin/listinfo/i18n">i18n mailing list</ulink> of OTRS.
        The OTRS team will take care of regenerating the XML documenation for your language.
    </para>
    <important>
        <para>
            Especially if you add a new translation, it is recommended to send in snapshots of your file regularly
            to make sure that your translation has the correct structure and that the docbook documentation
            can be successfully generated from it, producing valid XML documents.
        </para>
    </important>
    <para>
        If you want to test your translation file locally, you can checkout the doc-admin repository
        and use po4a directly to generate the translation files. Please see the file <literal>po4a.conf</literal>
        in the top directory of that module for usage hints. For additional questions, please use the i18n mailing list.
    </para>
</section>
