<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">

<section id="dynamic-fields-overview">
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>
        Dynamic Fields are custom fields that can be added to a screen to enhance and add
        information to an object (e.g. a ticket or an article).
    </para>
    <para>
        The Dynamic Fields are the evolution of the ticket and article Free Fields
        ( "TikcetFreeText", "TicketFreeKey", "TicketFreeTime", "ArticleFreeText", "ArticleFreeKey"
        and "ArticleFreeTime" ) from older versions of OTRS.
    </para>
    <para>
        From OTRS version 3.1 the old Free Fields has been replaced with the new Dynamic Fields,
        for a better backward compatibility and data preservation when updating from previous
        versions, a migration script has been developed to convert the existing Free Fields to
        Dynamic Fields and to move their values from the <emphasis>ticket</emphasis> and
        <emphasis>article</emphasis> tables in the database to new dynamic fields tables.
    </para>
    <note>
        <para>
            Any custom development that uses Free Fields needs to be ported to the new Dynamic
            Fields code structure, otherwise it will not work anymore. For this reason is very
            important to know that only updated installations of OTRS has the old Free
            Fields converted to Dynamic Fields, new or clean installations of OTRS has no Dynamic
            Fields defined "out of the box" and any Dynamic Field needed by the custom development
            needs to be added.
        </para>
    </note>
    <para>
        The restriction on the number of the fields per ticket or article has been removed, this
        means that a ticket or article could have as many fields as needed. and now it is also
        possible to use the Dynamic Fields framework for other objects rather than just ticket or
        article.
    </para>
    <para>
        The new Dynamic Fields can store the same data types as the Free Fields
        (Text and Date/Time), and they can be also defined as them (Single line input, drop-down and
        date-time). but Dynamic Fields goes beyond that, a new data type: Integer, has been added
        and also new options to define the fields like Multiple-line inputs, check-boxes,
        Multiple-select and date (without time) fields. Each field type defines its own data type.
    </para>
    <para>
        Due to its modular design each Dynamic Field type can be seen as a plug-in to a framework,
        and this plug-in can be a OTRS standard package to extend the available types of the
        Dynamic Fields.
    </para>
</section>
